<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-08-15T04:05:27+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Novin Ghaffari</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Unpredictable Trends</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Unpredictable-Trends/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unpredictable Trends" /><published>2023-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Unpredictable-Trends</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Unpredictable-Trends/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="chaotic-signals">Chaotic Signals</h2>

<p>There are a few considerations when dealing with chaotic trends that this article highlights:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>complex etiologies</strong>: volatile patterns typically exhibit complex causes. Disentangling a phenomenon’s complicated origins enables better prediction of its future patterns.</li>
  <li><strong>measurement uncertainty</strong>: data and trends are often treated as certain fact. In reality most data is collected and curated by humans and human systems. This creates a real possibility for measurement errors as well as discrepancies arising from measurement methodologies.</li>
  <li><strong>external covariates</strong>: the fundamental process behind scientific reasoning is crucial for taming seemingly unpredictable trends: associating some variables to the outcome of others. With robust patterns of association between variables we can use information on accessible variables to predict outcomes in (potentially directly inaccessible) variables.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-worlds-gone-mad">The World’s Gone Mad</h2>

<p>The labor data from the United States appears to show a mass disabling event occurring from 2020 through 2023. This data is collected by the US Bureau of Labor Statistics and aggregated and published by the Federal Reserve of St. Louis’ economic data research unit (FRED)<d-cite key="FRED2023"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>From July 2010 to July 2020, the total disabled population increased from about 26 million to 29 million. That is an increase of about 11.5% over 10 years, or an annual increase of about 1.1%. From July 2020 to July 2023, the disabled population increased from 29 million to about 34 million. That translates to an increase of 17.2% over 3 years, or an annual growth of 5.4%.</p>

<div class="embed-container">
  <iframe src="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/graph/graph-landing.php?g=17QX9&amp;width=670&amp;height=475" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="overflow:hidden;" allowtransparency="true" loading="lazy"></iframe>
</div>

<script src="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/graph/js/embed.js" type="text/javascript"></script>

<p>The causes of this sudden rise in the disabled population are contested. Some theories tie the increased disabling to long covid. While some studies have shown most long covid symptoms abate within a year, others contend that certain effects, such as chronic fatigue, may persist<d-cite key="bonuck2023"></d-cite>. Others think environmental toxins, the legacy of pandemic era policies (e.g. reduced general medical visits), climate change, and host of other factors many driving the increased disabling. Still others think changes in reporting standards may be contributing. In all likelihood, there is a convergence of different factors driving an increase of this magnitude.</p>]]></content><author><name>Novin Ghaffari</name></author><category term="AI/ML," /><category term="business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A survey of current chaotic trends and a discussion on managing unpredictability]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Musings on Persian Poetry</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Persian-Poetry/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Musings on Persian Poetry" /><published>2023-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Persian-Poetry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Persian-Poetry/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="four-poems-from-four-poets">Four Poems from Four Poets</h2>

<p>Out of boredom, during the late nights of my childhood, I would often crack open books of Persian poetry. Reading translations in English first and then in the original Persian as my proficiency in literary Persian grew. I was bedazzled by how these poets crafted literary art from wordsmithing, illustrating vivid scenes, capturing passionate emotions, and revealing essential truths and wisdom. Some came easy, others took longer to begin understanding. In this post I want to share a few favorite pieces, four small excerpts of longer poems written by four different poets of Persian, and all giants in their own right. After each I provide my own translation. I have tried to keep rhyme scheme and meaning intact, but it is impossible to maintain the meter as Persian and Persian poetry have very different types from English. I default to iambic meter here. After translations I also try to provide some clarity and insight into the meaning.</p>

<h2 id="poems-translations-and-meanings">Poems, Translations, and Meanings</h2>

<p>The first piece is from Omar Khayyam (1048-1113), the Persian polymath who is credited with writing a series of rubaiyat (a style of poetry where in every four lines, lines one, two, and four rhyme), though some believe this is a misattribution. His poetry was first “translated” into English by Edward Fitzgerald (1809-1883) (translation should be understood loosely here, Fitzgerald himself acknowledged it was half translation and half his own inspiration from Khayyam’s work). This translation was once the most widely read work of poetry in the world. I really began my forays into poetry with Khayyam. His poems were always simpler, even in the original Persian. However, this one would stumble me at first.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>در کارگه کوزه گری رفتم دوش</p>

  <p>دیدم دو هزار کوزه گویا و خموش</p>

  <p>ناگاه یکی کوزه برآورد خروش</p>

  <p>کو کوزه گر و کوزه خر و کوزه فروش</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>To the potter’s workshop, I went last night,</p>

  <p>Saw two thousand pots, some glib, some not quite,</p>

  <p>When suddenly one pot screamed such insight,</p>

  <p>Asking, “who makes and trades us pots?” outright!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I eventually came to understand that the pots represented people (possibly a reference to the Biblical and Quranic idea that man is made of clay). Some are talkative, some are quiet doing their own thing. But none ask the relevant questions, save for one, the existential thinker and questioner among man. In short, the meaning can be summarized itself with a short poetic line: “Few think, few ponder, few question, few wonder.”</p>

<p>The next one comes from Sa’di of Shiraz (1210-1292). He was from the city of Shiraz in Southern Iran. Due to conflicts and the Mongol invasions his family moved westward. He had a long, decorated life before becoming a poet. His experiences included being captured by crusaders and made a slave for several years. Having seen some of the best and worst of humanity, Sa’di wrote a famous poem about empathy being at the heart of humanity. This poem currently graces the entrance of the United Nations (maybe a subject for a later post). Sa’di’s work is known for its practical wisdom. In one story he relates the tale of an old wrestler who teaches a young man his moves. At one point the teacher is forced to wrestle his student. Here the teacher pulls out a move the student never learned. When perplexed the teacher explains that one must always have a proverbial ‘ace up their sleeve,’ you never know when you need it. This poem, also a rubaiyat, is another example of practical wisdom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>دانی که چه گفت زال با رستم گرد</p>

  <p>دشمن نتوان حقیر و بیچاره شمرد</p>

  <p>دیدیم بسی که آب سرچشمه خرد</p>

  <p>چون بیشتر آمد شتر و بار ببرد</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Do you know what Zal told Rostam the hero of repute?</p>

  <p>“Never regard your beaten foe as ‘down-and-out’ to boot,</p>

  <p>Many we saw drinking from the stream in triumph,</p>

  <p>As more camels came from behind, stealing all of the loot!”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rostam was a legendary hero and warrior in Iranian mythology, and Zal was his dad. Here Zal counsels him to never discount the enemy, even after a defeat. For one quick ruse can turn everything upside down on its head. Here the one foolishly celebrating his victory has to contend with the enemy creeping from behind and stealing all of the battle loot. Bottom line: “it isn’t over ‘til it’s over.”</p>

<p>The next one comes from the poet Jalaladdin Balkhi (1207-1273). He is famous in Iran as ‘Molavi.’ In the West he is popularly known as ‘Rumi.’ Born in the city of Balkh in Afghanistan, his family moved to escape the Mongol invasions, to Iran first, then to Konya in modern Turkey. He became deeply steeped in mystical philosophies, and the whirling dervishes today in Konya are descended from his mystical tradition. Love, especially the deeply philosophical love of his mysticism, is a frequent topic. Khayyam used to be the most widely read poet. Today it is Rumi (although the most popular translation is by an individual who acknowledges they have no knowledge of Persian and just piece together different translations, modifying as they feel fit!). In this poem he talks about how the superficial notion of love rooted in physical attraction is an illusion. This poem is written in the style of ‘masnavi’ or heroic couplets.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>آنچ بر صورت تو عاشق گشته ای</p>

  <p>چون برون شد جان چرایش هشته ای</p>

  <p>صورتش بر جاست این سیری ز چیست</p>

  <p>عاشقا واجو که معشوق تو کیست</p>

</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>That on the face of it that made you into a lover,</p>

  <p>Once the life has departed then why do you feel other?</p>

  <p>The face is in place, then what is this satiety there?</p>

  <p>Who is really your beloved? Oh, lovers beware!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here when Rumi says the life has departed, he means when someone has died and become a corpse. One might find a face attractive and think that is why they covet that person. Yet when that person has died, even when the face is the same (before decomposition of course), generally people do not feel attraction any more. He’s hinting that there’s something deeper there that’s attracting the person to his or her beloved. He goes on to explicate this point in the rest of the poem. He likens the face to a beautiful wall. The wall’s beauty means nothing until the rays of light reveal its form and image. The light is the character and consciousness of a person behind the face.</p>

<p>The last poem comes to us from Hafez of Shiraz (1325-1390). He was the last of the classical Persian poets who composed poetry on mystical love. He acquired the nickname Hafez (meaning one who memorizes) for supposedly having memorized the Quran forwards and backwards by age 9, though this may be apocryphal. In reality very little concrete information is known about his life. In this poem he extols the virtue of finding inside yourself what you may be seeking in others.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>سال ها دل طلب جام جم از ما می کرد</p>

  <p>وان چه خود داشت ز بیگانه تمنا می کرد</p>

  <p>گوهری کز صدف کون و مکان بیرون است</p>

  <p>طلب از گمشدگان لب دریا می کرد</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>For years my heart sought the holy grail, searching mad,</p>

  <p>Begging of strangers for what it already had,</p>

  <p>How my heart pled with lost souls scattered on the shore,</p>

  <p>While there on the beach lay life’s hidden pearl unclad!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hafez’s point: sometimes you already have what you need!</p>]]></content><author><name>Novin Ghaffari</name></author><category term="languages," /><category term="history" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some translations and thoughts on four poetic excerpts from four of the giants of Persian poetry]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From History to Business Part I: Scouting</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/History-Business-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From History to Business Part I: Scouting" /><published>2023-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/History-Business-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/History-Business-1/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-history-to-business-series">The ‘History to Business’ Series</h2>

<p>This post inaugurates a series titled, ‘From History to Business.’ The aim here is to connect principles and philosophies from ancient warfare to modern business. This genre is already quite popular. Books on ancient warfare stratagems, like Sun Tzu’s <em>Art of War</em> and Miyamoto Musashi’s <em>Book of Five Rings</em>, have found renewed interest and readership when repackaged as business stratagem guides. As a lifelong, avid student of history, my goal here is to provide links from my own historical readings to modern business strategy principles. For this first part, I will focus on <strong>scouting</strong>, its importance in the ancient world, and its utility in business environments.</p>

<h2 id="seek-and-you-shall-find">Seek and You Shall Find</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“…seek and you will find; knock and the door will be opened to you.” - Matthew 7:7</p>
</blockquote>

<p>War is costly and taxing. Warfare drains a nation or organization of its vital resources. War can also be unpredictable. Surprise attacks and ambushes can take down mighty armies. Natural disasters and tumultuous terrain can upend an army’s campaign. Internal strife and discord can dismantle an army from within. Precluding all these possibilities absolutely is an impossibility. Precluding these possibilities to the greatest degree possible requires something: <em>intelligence</em>. Here we refer to ‘scouting’ loosely as the process of deliberately seeking and obtaining intelligence. In the ancient world among the ancient armies, scouting was largely a physical process. Today much of scouting and intelligence gathering is nonphysical, but the same principles apply.</p>

<p>Scouting and gathering information fulfills several important intelligence objectives in relation to warfare. These include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Knowing the battlefield</li>
  <li>Understanding the enemy</li>
  <li>Reckoning supplies and supply lines</li>
</ul>

<p>The importance of each has been elucidated in numerous works on the topic of war stratagems. For example, on the first point Sun Tzu notes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Whoever is first in the field and awaits the coming of the enemy, will be fresh for the fight; whoever is second in the field and has to hasten to battle will arrive exhausted.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>On the second point, Tzu writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If you know the enemy and know yourself, you need not fear the result of a hundred battles. If you know yourself but not the enemy, for every victory gained you will also suffer a defeat. If you know neither the enemy nor yourself, you will succumb in every battle.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And on the third point, Sun Tzu has also offered numerous opinions. While scouting strategies date back to time immemorial, intelligence, scouting, and espionage reached a zenith of mastery under the Assyrian empire. The Assyrian people arose in the fertile enclave of Northern Mesopotamia, centered around the city of Ashur and expanding from there. As an agrarian people on the crossroads of what was then the civilized world, Assyria came under frequent attacks and raids from her neighbors. It was said in ancient Assyria that a man sows his fields with a plow in one hand and a sword in the other. As a result of this environment, Assyria developed into a formidable, warlike empire on several occasions. They attained an advanced level of sophistication with regards to warfare, having a well-regimented army, well-designed supply lines, and a complex espionage network. The Assyrian empire and its military apparatus are studied by modern militaries, including at the US Army War College.</p>

<p>The military organization of the Assyrian empire reached an unparalleled level of development during the neo-Assyrian period (roughly 900-600 BC). During this period the king kept a network of internal informants who would maintain confidential communications between the king and his provincial governors. This allowed the central government to keep tabs on all corners of the empire and receive advance notice of developing threats. The Assyrians also maintained a network of external spies. This allowed the Assyrians to monitor situations in neighboring civilizations, to thwart potential attacks, to collect necessary information for their own campaigns, and to engage in sabotage and subterfuge. Additionally, the Assyrian army had units specialized for scouting. This was important for assessing the food and supply situation alongside assessing hostile threats within each theater of operation. The highly developed scouting and intelligence gathering of the Assyrians was critical to their military efficacy<d-cite key="dubovsky2006"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>In the wake of the destruction and reorganization left behind by the Assyrian empire, new nations started to form in the ancient Middle East. In southern Iran, the predominant civilization had been Elam, a major rival of Babylon and Assyria. Elam was eventually devastated by the Assyrian empire under Ashurbanipal. He openly brags in his chronicles about the brutality and butchery that he wrought upon Elam. He even gloated about sowing salt into their fields to make them infertile and to guarantee that the Elamites would never arise again. While the Assyrians were looking to secure their own position by removing a critical opponent, they overlooked the bigger picture. And while their scouting in the immediate vicinity of their empire was impeccable, they had gaps in their intelligence when it came to regions beyond. And indeed, from regions beyond new entrants were entering the arena. Indo-European speaking Aryan tribes were entering the Iranian Plateau (the word ‘Iran’ itself means ‘land of the Aryans’), gradually replacing the Elamite civilization with their own polities, namely the Mede and Persian kingdoms. The Medes would eventually team up with Babylonians further South to eliminate the Assyrians.</p>

<p>The Median kingdom was replaced by the Persian empire (about 550-330 BC), which fully integrated the Medes (a closely related tribe to Persians). As the Indo-European stock of these Iranian kingdoms came from a background of animal husbandry (particularly cattle) and horseback riding, they were fundamentally a more mobile population, at the time, then more sedentary peoples further West in the Middle East. Hence scouting came naturally to them and was a skill they employed. The founder of the first Persian empire (the Achaemenid dynasty) was Cyrus the Great, immortalized in the Bible. He built the largest empire the world had seen at the time. Much of the impetus for this task came from Cyrus’ visionary perspective that was fueled by his passion for learning about the world around him. Even as a child, Cyrus was supposed to have asked every trader and traveler about the lands that they had visited. These inquiries helped him build a mental map of the peoples and civilizations he would later have to interact with during his expansionism (Cyrus was also reputed for his deep respect and tolerance of the cultures he interacted with). Likewise, during his campaigns, special cavalry units would be sent out to gather information, assess terrain, and determine hostile threats. These scouts and their gathered intelligence were critical to the success of Cyrus’ campaigns. For example, during the campaign against Babylon, the Persians learnt that they would have to cross a major river. With this information Cyrus brought a team of engineers who devised a plan for crossing the river with the army: using inflated animal skins to carry troops and supplies.</p>

<p>Later when Darius the Great took the reigns of the empire, he implemented a new system of administration for governance. The empire was divided into satrapies, provinces with local governors called ‘satraps.’ Along with this reorganization, Darius implemented several reforms that allowed for the rapid scouting of intelligence. First, he built a system of roads connecting major hubs in the empire. On this road system, he built a postal system. This courier system was composed of a series of stations along the roads with fresh horses. Messages would pass between stations; at each new station a new rider would take the message(s) and leave on a fresh horse while the incoming rider would find an opportunity to reset. This allowed for the (relatively) rapid transmission of information from one corner of the empire to the other. Finally, similar to the Assyrian informant network, Darius created his own informant network called the ‘eyes and ears of the king.’ This network would continuously relay information to the king about the events and circumstances in each province. The Achaemenid dynasty lasted a fair while for such a large empire. This was largely driven by the ability of the central government to scout critical information in a timely manner and to act on it<d-cite key="olmstead1948"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Fast forward to the 600s AD, a new force was on the rise in the Middle East. The prophet, Muhammad (SAWS), unified the previously disunited Arabian tribes under the banner of the new religion of Islam. Muhammad’s rise to power was fraught with conflict with the polytheistic tribes of the Hijaz in Western Arabia. Muhammad’s success in these campaigns against the polytheists largely drew on his superior acquisition and incorporation of intelligence. This can clearly be seen in the first major skirmish between the newly formed Muslims of Medina and polytheistic Meccans, the Battle of Badr. As a Meccan trade caravan returning from Syria was passing by Medina, the Muslims were wary of attacks and raids. Muhammad encouraged the Medinans to join him on a proactive campaign in anticipation of a polytheistic attack. As soon Muhammad left the city, he and others approached local Bedouin tribes, inquiring about their knowledge of the affairs. Muhammad realized that the local tribes between Mecca and Medina were aware of him and his troop movements. They were also keenly aware of the Meccan trade caravans (many of them earned extra income by servicing the wealthy trade caravans that passed through). From this Muhammad could garner that both sides were under constant observation by the locals and that the Meccans would be able to obtain information about him as easily as he did about them. Wanting to stay ahead of the curve, Muhammad sent out scouts to survey the surrounding areas and gather further information. The Muslim scouts were able to converse with a few members of the Meccan caravan. They found out that although most of the caravanners had no desire to fight and were looking to return home, a particularly fanatical faction led by Abu Jahl, had formed. This faction organized itself militarily and split from the rest of the trade caravan, seeking to find and fight the Muslims. Muhammad himself during a scouting mission asked someone about how many camels this group would butcher every night. The informant revealed that it was about 9-10 camels. From this Muhammad could surmise that their strength was about 1000 (presumably each camel would feed 100-110 mouths). The Medinans only had a force of 313, a major disadvantage. To mitigate this imbalance, Muhammad decided to take the battlefield first. By doing this, he was able to identify all the major watering holes on the battlefield and position his troops so as to block the enemy’s access. Because of this scouting of intelligence and quick thinking, the Muslim army was able to rout an opponent over 3 times their size at the Battle of Badr.</p>

<p>The vaults of history are loaded with many more examples of the importance of scouting and intelligence gathering to military success, from the Mongol empire to the British empire. Here we shall conclude this section with one more example: the Battle of Okehazama (Japan, 1560). In the Owari province in south central Japan, a new and unexpected leader, Oda Nobunaga, had risen to power about a decade earlier. Due to his brash, cavalier attitude, many in the province did not view Oda Nobunaga as fit for leadership. The subsequent history would reveal Nobunaga to be a cunning general and a genius strategist, albeit quite a brutal and sadistic one. Early in his career, a warlord from the East, Imagawa Yoshimoto, had his sights set on the capital, then Kyoto. To get to Kyoto he had to pass through Owari, so he intended on capturing Owari on his way. Fielding a force of over 25000 troops, he outnumbered Nobunaga’s forces by about 10:1. Early on Yoshimoto’s forces captured several peripheral castles without much resistance. Nobunaga’s generals begged him to hole up in his castle, in a defensible position, to try to outlast the inevitable siege. This irked Nobunaga who had no intention of being a sitting duck. Furthermore, he had placed a network of scouts and informants throughout the province and had a steady stream of intelligence. He came to understand that though the invading force was much larger, they had spread themselves out trying to canvas the entire province. Having made inroads without much resistance, Yoshimoto and a smaller contingent of troops were already celebrating the perceived victory at a captured castle in Okehazama. Nobunaga saw this as a “do-or-die” moment. He took the bulk of his troops out to confront Yoshimoto at Okehazama, hoping to cut off the serpent’s head. When they reached the site, the situation was more favorable than they could have imagined. It was a hot and stormy summer day. So, most of Yoshimoto’s forces had removed their armor and were drinking in celebration of their imminent victory. With this non-defensive posture, Nobunaga’s troops were able to surprise Yoshimoto and his contingent, routing their forces and killing Yoshimoto. With their leader deceased, the rest of Yoshimoto’s troops abandoned their posts and fled the province. Nobunaga was able to defeat a numerically far superior opponent through the use of scouting and immediately acting on pertinent information<d-cite key="samson1961"></d-cite>.</p>

<h2 id="business-connections">Business Connections</h2>

<p>To finish, let us connect the principle of scouting to business strategy. Just like the battlefield, the business environment can be unpredictable. Circumstances are volatile and change is inevitable. Many giants of the business world and dinosaurs of industry have eventually succumbed to the winds of change. While there are no guarantees, the best way to stay abreast of potential changes is by continuously scouting. That is, continuously gathering information on the business environment and market dynamics. Examples of firms that have failed to do this abound.</p>

<p>Blockbuster, a titan of the movie industry, eventually gave way to Netflix and streaming services. Blockbuster missed several opportunities to transform its business model to meet the demands of the increasingly digital consumer, including an early opportunity to purchase Netflix<d-cite key="frankbitter2023"></d-cite>. Kodak, the giant of classical photography, was reluctant to invest in up-and-coming digital technology during the late 1990s. As a result, Kodak did not understand the coming digital revolution nor did it understand the revolution in handheld device technology. By the late 2000s, even sales of digital cameras dropped as people resorted to using cellphones and tablets for photography<d-cite key="tristan2023"></d-cite>. Circuit City, a popular electronics store, went bust in the 2010s, giving way to competitors like BestBuy, Walmart, and Amazon. Their operations suffered from several setbacks that stem from not understanding their consumer base. Their stores were at inconvenient locations, especially compared to competitors like Walmart. With the advent of Amazon and internet shopping, this inconvenience became even more of a hassle in the consumer’s mind. Furthermore, seeking to cut costs, Circuit City reduced the quality of their service. Staff reductions and the hiring of inexperienced, cheap labor brought this quality down. In the end, Circuit City was not able to turn its inventory and had to file for bankruptcy<d-cite key="cohan2021"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>In each of these cases, the woes of these businesses arose from an inability to understand the market dynamics and emerging trends. A healthy dose of scouting and researching trends might have led to the implementation of strategies that could have mitigated the eventual downfall. As a fast-paced business operating in a competitive environment, it is critical to keep tabs on any relevant industry trends. Failure to do so can lead to something surprising coming out of left field and bringing down the business.</p>

<p>Until the next post in this series, keep scouting!</p>]]></content><author><name>Novin Ghaffari</name></author><category term="business," /><category term="history" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The importance of scouting in ancient warfare and modern business]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Posture: Positioning for Health and Success</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Posture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Posture: Positioning for Health and Success" /><published>2023-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Posture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/Posture/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="stop-slouching">Stop Slouching!</h2>

<p>“Sit up straight and stop slouching!” Words one might hear from a doting grandparent. Growing up, older generations did not have cellphones, tablets, gaming devices, laptops, and desktops that younger generations must contend with. Average life back in the day was also far more physical. That and people interacted face-to-face far more than our overconnected, constantly-plugged-in, post-pandemic generations. As a consequence, there was a clear, intuitive understanding about good posture. Even as recently as my childhood, when I was a bit of bookworm and developed a bit (actually quite a bit) of bad posture, I recall how most people around me had decent, strong posture. Sadly, among today’s up-and-coming generations mirred in hours of screen time, my old posture would not seem abnormal.</p>

<h2 id="types-and-origins-of-postural-imbalances">Types and Origins of Postural Imbalances</h2>

<p>Prolonged poor posture can result in muscular imbalances in holding pattern and subsequent disorder and dysfunction of the vertebrae. While each individual’s exact alignment may differ, common categories of postural imbalance include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>lumbar hyperlordosis</strong>: the ‘donald duck’ butt, with an excessively tight lower abdomen and weak glutes pulling the hips back</li>
  <li><strong>swayback</strong>: the opposite of hyperlordosis, tight glutes push the hips forward and in front of the rest of the torso</li>
  <li><strong>kyphosis</strong>: abnormally convex curvature of the upper thoracic spine, a C-spine</li>
  <li><strong>scoliosis</strong>: a curvature of the spine in the frontal plane, i.e. from side-to-side</li>
  <li><strong>winged scapula</strong>: an abnormal protrusion of the scapula behind the shoulder, often due to an imbalance of serratus anterior muscles</li>
  <li><strong>forward head posture</strong>: excessive forward curvature of the cervical vertebrae</li>
</ul>

<p>These postural imbalances arise from a combination of stressors and poor positioning throughout daily life. For instance, one study compared 30 workers (group I) who worked at a computer for 6h+ and 30 individuals who rarely worked with computers (group II). Both the angle of protusion of the head (measuring across precise points on the head and neck) and center of gravity (via computerized dynamic posturography) were measured. Statistically significant differences (\(p&lt;.05\)) between groups were measured between groups. Group I had a greater average angle of foward head posture, and a greater average anterior tilt in center of gravity<d-cite key="kangetal2012"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Another study examined the link between cell phone use duration and forward head posture and associated pain/fatigue. A sample of 34 adults were divided into 3 groups: 11 used for 10 minutes, 12 used for 20 minutes, and 11 used for 30 minutes. Group 2 showed elevated fatigue in the upper left trapezius. Group 3 showed elevated fatigue in the left cervical erector spinae and across both upper trapezius muscles. Measurements of pain showed that all groups had greater average pain after use, and group 3 had greater pain than group 1 after use as well. The study demonstrated how excessive cell phone use induces muscular imbalances that can lead to forward head posture and other postural misalignments. The study recommended observing correct posture while using cell phone and tablet devices alongside frequent breaks of 20 minutes or longer<d-cite key="kimkoo2016"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Yet another study looked at the impact of intense mental concentration alongside psychosocial stressors on forward head posture and muscular activation. Participants were given challenging work on a computer, and some participants were further subjected to various stressors. Intense concentration alone produced forward head posture and stress did not add much to the effect in this study. However, stress was associated with a significant activation, as measured by electromyography, in the upper trapezius muscles. This study indicated that stress may be carried primarily in the trapezius muscles. Over time this may result in faulty recruitment patterns and further postural misalignments. The authors emphasized stress prevention in workplaces to prevent trapezius myalagia<d-cite key="shahidietal2013"></d-cite>.</p>

<h2 id="health-effects-of-postural-imbalance">Health Effects of Postural Imbalance</h2>

<p>Postural imbalances have been linked to a host of health ailments and even accelerated aging. This section details a few possible ill-effects of posture misalignment. This is not exhaustive but gives a sense of the sorts of the generative conditions that can arise from chronic postural imbalance.</p>

<p>One research group at the University of Leeds found a connection between neck posture and changes in cardiorespiration. The team was motivated by previous findings that chiropractic manipulations, particularly of the C1 vertebrae, can induce changes in blood pressure. Their research revealed that the muscles of the neck, especially the suboccipital muscle group, send afferent signals to the intermedius of the medulla, a brain stem component. In turn this part of the brainstem sends signals to the nucleus of the solitary tract (NTS). The NTS is directly involved in altering cardiorespiratory variables such as blood pressure and breathing rate. In short, the evidence suggests that crooked neck really could be cranking up the blood pressure <d-cite key="edwardsetal2007"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Indeed proper respiration, that is deep, diaphragmatic breathing, has itself been associated with a host of health benefits<d-cite key="hamasaki2020"></d-cite>. The diaphragm is the primary muscle of respiration. Nonetheless the musculature of the neck, chest, and upper back, such as the scalenes, sternocleidomastoid, and trapezius muscles, also play an auxiliary role in ventilation. Proper engagement of these muscles opens the airways for breathing, and imbalances can lead to constrictions in the breathing passage and shallow breathing patterns. However the direction of the relationship between good posture and good breathing practice is a case of ‘chicken or the egg.’ On the one hand some studies have found poor posture to impede respiration. One study found forward head posture reduced respiratory capacity and impinged on lower thoracic and diaphragmatic mobility, directly decreasing respiratory function<d-cite key="kosekietal2019"></d-cite>. On the other hand, observance of better breathing habits has been shown to improve posture and mobility. One study measured the impact of breathing exercises on posture and spinal mobility in female university students as compared to yoga and pilates. The study concluded that physiotherapeutic breathing exercises were as effective as yoga and pilates at improving spinal mobility and correcting postural imbalances <d-cite key="csepregietal2022"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>A study out of Japan found a strong association between poor posture and cognitive decline. The study sampled 411 individuals from 50-89 years of age, analyzing inviduals within decade of age (50s, 60s, etc.) and by gender (202 male, 209 female). Participants took two different cognitive assessments and had their sagittal spinal balance (front to back) measured through radiological methods. The spinal imbalance in the sagittal plane was measured as the sagittal vertical axis. The study found sagittal vertical axis anteriorization (SVAA) (i.e. forward leaning) was significantly associated with cognitive decline. For males SVAA &gt; 70 mm over 80, &gt; 90 mm over 70, and &gt; 100 mm at any age were more likely to exhibit cognitive decline. For women at any age, SVAA &gt; 70 mm was associated with increased risks of cognitive decline. For clear radiological images of SVAA, see ‘figure 3’ in the paper <d-cite key="nishimuraetal2022"></d-cite>.</p>

<h2 id="additional-content">Additional Content</h2>

<p>For a fun talk on posture, see fitness expert Roger Frampton’s TEDx talk:
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jOJLx4Du3vU">Why Sitting Down Destroys You - Roger Frampton</a></p>

<p>For a quick but informative clip see Murat Dalkilinç’s TED-Ed presentation:
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OyK0oE5rwFY">The Benefits of Good Posture</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Novin Ghaffari</name></author><category term="exercise" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An glance at the importance of posture in health and well-being]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hiring in the Age of AI: Hope and Fear</title><link href="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/AI-hiring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hiring in the Age of AI: Hope and Fear" /><published>2023-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/AI-hiring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alshedivat.github.io/blog/2023/AI-hiring/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="changing-job-markets">Changing Job Markets</h2>

<p>The information age has fundamentally altered many processes in society. The availability of vast amounts of information coupled with advanced data processing mechanisms has facilitated an increasing emphasis on “data-driven” strategies among organizations. Large firms and institutions are increasingly turning toward data-derived insights to inform and to support decision making. The hiring process is one domain already feeling the effects of these changes.</p>

<p>The hiring process can be a painful, drawn out, cumbersome, and downright expensive process. And that holds for both job seekers and job recruiters. For job hunters, the search for a decent position is time-consuming, often involving dozens, if not hundreds, of applications each filled with cycles of interviews, document drafting, aptitude and skills assessments, and negotiations. Even competent and accomplished candidates can find themselves drifting for months in search of a fitting role. For the job seekers, there is also an unfair asymmetry at play; their position during the hiring process is usually a big unknown. Recruitees are often left guessing how likely they are to land a position, how stiff the competition is, what work culture characteristics the recruiting firm is looking for, and so on. It is a typical practice for mid to large size firms to take multiple candidates through the entire interview process, knowing full well that most candidates will not be offered any position. These candidates are only being entertained as alternates and to fill hiring process quotas. The whole process can be an immense drain on a job seeker’s time, and as the old adage goes, “time is money.”</p>

<p>The recruitment process can also be stressful and costly on the hiring side. Finding the right candidate for an open position typically involves casting a wide net, sifting through voluminous quantities of resumes, cover letters, and applications. Giving due attention to the right candidates is time-consuming and difficult for firms without large resources to devote to the recruitment process. Hiring for a new type of role presents an added difficulty; if a firm does not have much experience in a technical area, it can be hard to assess the quality and fit of candidates for such a new type of role. And even when firms hone in on a stellar candidate, it is not unusal for top talent to be sitting on multiple job offers. If they decide their services will be more valued elsewhere, that leaves the firm having to restart their hiring process for the position all over again.</p>

<h2 id="ai-hiring-and-human-biases">AI, Hiring, and Human Biases</h2>

<p>With dozens, hundreds, and sometimes even thousands of applicants for a position, a manual review of all candidate applications can be labor intensive, even prohibitively so. Here hiring algorithms can help curtail costs and labor time. Things as simple as filtering based on keywords can reduce the candidate pool a hiring manager must look over. On the other end of the spectrum, approaches like AI deep learning and computer vision can be deployed for in-depth evaluation of a job candidates’ facial expression. However, the process of incorporating data science and AI into hiring practices can be fraught with hiccups and biases.</p>

<p>There is a notion that ‘data science and analytics’ is a neutral, unbiased mechanism for analyzing data and making data-driven decisions. There is a bit of truth here. AI and machine learning, deployed effectively, can help reduce bias. By combing through vast volumes of data, more than a human could process in a feasible amount of time, data analytics and algorithms can facilitate data-driven decision making. By deploying rigorous analytic techniques, rooted in mathematics and statistics, AI and machine learning also remove some of the inherent biases of relying solely on human opinion and intuition. Nonetheless there is still arbitrariness in the choice of algorithm and in the choice of data processing and modeling methodologies. To assume that data analytics can completely remove all biases is a mistake. As Gideon Mann and Cathy O’Neil observe writing for the <strong>Harvard Business Review</strong> <d-cite key="gideononeil2016"></d-cite>,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Algorithms are, in part, our opinions embedded in code. They reflect human biases and prejudices that lead to machine learning mistakes and misinterpretations. This bias shows up in numerous aspects of our lives, including algorithms used for electronic discovery, teacher evaluations, car insurance, credit score rankings, and university admissions.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>With all of the benefits and detriments, big data and AI is revolutionizing the modern hiring process. A 2018 survey of over 8800 hiring managers conducted by LinkedIn revealed the following trends. A total of 67% of hiring managers claimed to use AI in hiring, claiming it helped reduce biases (43%), deliver the best candidate matches (31%). Respondents claimed AI Is helpful for sourcing candidates (58%), screening candidates (56%), and nurturing candidates (55%). Furthermore, hiring managers pointed out that big data and talent intelligence from past hires has been used to increase retention (56%), evaluate skill gaps (50%), and build better offers (50%) <d-cite key="linkedin2018"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Many hiring and candidate selection algorithms are trained on past hiring data. The idea: by identifying the data patterns of successful past hires’ applications and searching for similar patterns in current job applicants’ application, a firm can replicate past hiring successes. While this seems like a good strategy, it does suffer from a major pitfall: training on past hire data, an algorithm not only learns past hiring patterns, but also all the biases associated with past hires. For instance, Marianne Bertrand and Sendhil Mullainathan in a study for the National Bureau of Economic Research, found that resumes with white names were 50% more likely to receive callbacks as compared to resumes with African-American names. Furthermore, a high-quality resume with a white-sounding name elicited 30% more callbacks, whereas increases for a high-quality resume with an African American name only showed marginal increases in callbacks. Furthermore, these patterns of biases and discrimination were observed across the board, being equally present with employers who listed ‘Equal Opportunity Employer’ in their job ads <d-cite key="bertrandmullainathan2003"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Indeed, the reckless, unscrupulous deployment of AI algorithms on past hiring data means that the learning algorithm will likely train on and learn all the past mistakes, prejudices, and biases in the hiring process. The next case study is one such case.</p>

<h2 id="a-big-data-hiring-failure-the-amazon-case">A Big Data Hiring Failure: The Amazon Case</h2>

<p>A naïve hiring algorithm that solely and blindly learns from past hiring decisions would likely replicate these biases moving forward. An example of this was automated job applicant filtering program deployed at Amazon. In 2014, with over half a million employees and growing, Amazon decided to use an algorithmic approach to improve its hiring efficiency. AI algorithms were devised at Amazon’s Edinburgh engineering hub to recognize over 50,000 resume terms, ranking job applicants from one to five stars. Training the algorithms on past hiring data, the AI picked up on and replicated a major facet of Amazon’s past hiring culture: male dominance. The algorithm implicitly upvoted resumes using language cues typically favored by male candidates. In fact, even if Amazon’s past hiring was fair in terms of gender, an AI algorithm can still learn unfair biases for future hiring decisions. That is, even if the best candidates for past positions were indeed mostly male, that does not mean that the best candidate for the next open position will conform to the same profile.</p>

<p>In addition to replicating gender bias, the complexity of the challenge led the hiring algorithms to select random, unqualified candidates on many occasions. After the discovery of these shortcomings, the project was scraped. Recently Amazon has revisited and revamped its automated hiring strategy, using AI for more straightforward tasks (e.g., removing duplicate applications) and for increasing diversity hires <d-cite key="dastin2018"></d-cite>.</p>

<h2 id="humantic-and-hirevue-more-case-studies">Humantic and HireVue: More Case Studies</h2>

<p>Some the most basic and fundamental analytical techniques used to assist in the hiring process are screening and filtering algorithms. In the simplest scenarios, these methods simply screen resumes looking for keywords that indicate good fit and qualification for a role. Naïve implementations of screening systems may cause employers to miss great candidates. However, even naïve implementations can save considerable time and resources. Some job positions receive thousands of applicants; when manually reviewed, each resume is glanced at for an average of a few seconds. Here screening can process more data in those few seconds than a human can manually consider. Adding a little sophistication in the form of some background analytics can provide even more information in little additional time. On the other end of the screening spectrum, Humantic claims to have a system that data mines candidates’ resumes. Using text analysis and psycholinguistics, the service is able to profile the personality of candidates without the need for additional testing. The service is used by more than 100 companies. As another example of the power of analytics, in a few milliseconds an AI system can calculate the approximate commute time based on a candidate’s location <d-cite key="heilweil2019"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>A striking example of AI in hiring is a system that goes far beyond simple filtering of resume terms. HireVue, a recruiting tech firm, has a developed an AI system that uses candidates web or mobile camera and microphone to assess candidates’ eye movements, facial patterns, diction, and tone of voice. These facial movements are used to assess a job candidate’s excitement, and they constitute 29% of a candidate’s score.  Based on these measurements, candidates are ranked against each other and given an ‘employability’ score. HireVue claims its AI can hone in on cues beyond just word choice on a resume. Among other things, HireVue claims that its AI systems are less prone to bias than human recruiters. They argue that AI can pick up on tiny signals that might be missed by human recruiter. A standard 30-minute HireVue assessment can generate as many as 500,000 data points. HireVue’s systems are currently used by many major employers, including Hilton and Unilever. Hilton has touted HireVue’s tech’s ability to reduce the average processing time for thousands of job applicants from 6 weeks to 5 days. Unilever claims HireVue’s systems have helped it reduce hiring labor hours by 100,000 and recruitment costs by $1 million <d-cite key="harwell2019"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, HireVue’s AI system has drawn a volley of criticism. One neuroscientist, Lisa Feldman Barret, led a meta-study reviewing 1000 published papers on computer vision and human emotion. Barret’s group concluded that these AI systems are highly effective at detecting and differentiating facial expressions, but not at signifying what they mean. Indeed, the significance of specific facial expressions are unique to different individuals, can vary by context, and vary widely in different cultures. Barrett relates the example of a frown, which may be taken as a cue of anger, hence a red flag for sales-type jobs. Nonetheless, a frown may also be indicative of intense focus, a potentially positive indicator of a hard work ethic. HireVue has countered these criticisms by claiming it has on-staff psychologists that work to tailor the scoring algorithm of their AI system to each client’s needs. Simon Mondal, the CEO of a job candidate screening platform, Ideal, which screens 5 million candidates a month, points out that these AI systems must be continually revisited and updated to prevent the encroachment of biases. Patterns always change, and the same is true in the field of hiring prospective candidates. Ultimately, a satisfactory AI screening system should be able to adjust its learning, and this generally requires human oversight. As Mondal points out, “You have to have a way to make sure that you aren’t picking people who are grouped in a specific way and that you’re only hiring those types of people” <d-cite key="heilweil2019"></d-cite>, <d-cite key="harwell2019"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>Potential concerns with the deployment of AI in hiring practices has even led to protective legislation. In the UK, a poll commissioned by the Royal Arts Society found that 60% of the public opposes the use of automated systems for hiring. Still, a YouGov poll found that only 32% are aware, in general, of the use of AI in decision-making, while only 14% are aware of its increasing adoption in recruitment and only 9% of its use in criminal justice <d-cite key="booth2019"></d-cite>. Public concern has begun converting into legislative action. In Illinois, state representative Jaime Andrade Jr. (D) co-sponsored “Public Act 101-0260,” a bill requiring employers in the state to notify job applicants of how their AI hiring systems work and to get the job applicant’s consent. Governor J.B. Pritzker signed the bill into law in August of 2019, and the bill went into law January of 2020 <d-cite key="harwell2019"></d-cite>. In November of 2019, lawyers at the Electronic Privacy Information Center (EPIC) filed a complaint with the FTC against HireVue on the grounds of potential bias, inaccuracy, and lacking transparency. The lawsuit also pointed to possible deceptive trade practices; HireVue claims it does not use facial recognition while EPIC contends its facial analysis constitutes facial recognition. The lawsuit came on the heels of congressional legislation that grants the FTC powers to investigate and regulate “automated decision systems” <d-cite key="heilweil2019"></d-cite>. Indeed, the rise of AI poses some challenges for antidiscrimination measures; in the worst case, a firm may attempt to hide biased recruiting policies behind algorithmic complexity. Already the Equal Employment Opportunities Commission (EEOC) has investigated several cases of alleged, AI-driven discrimination <d-cite key="opferetal2019"></d-cite>.</p>

<p>The hiring process can be complicated, painstaking, and time-consuming. The use of AI and machine learning offers a tremendous resource to manage and mitigate this complexity. As with all other technology, it brings its own share of promises and threats. The ultimate utility of this tech will largely be driven by how humans choose to adopt, use, and regulate it. Until people figure out how to relate AI and machine learning to hiring in an open, constructive way, the prospect of AI-led hiring will continue creating hope and fear.</p>]]></content><author><name>Novin Ghaffari</name></author><category term="AI/ML" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An overview of the potential benefits and possible drawbacks of the increasing use of AI hiring]]></summary></entry></feed>